<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discovery of a proiector shewing the beginning, progresse, and end of the projector and his projects : also the projectors last will and testament, with an epitaph to his memory / by T. Brugis, Gent.</title>
            <author>Brugis, Thomas, fl. 1640?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12240840</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12240840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 130:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discovery of a proiector shewing the beginning, progresse, and end of the projector and his projects : also the projectors last will and testament, with an epitaph to his memory / by T. Brugis, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Brugis, Thomas, fl. 1640?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 [i.e. 36], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.H., and are to be sold by Lawrence Chapman and William Cooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inventors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inventions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DISCOVERY OF A PROIECTOR. Shewing the beginning, progreſſe, and end of the Projector and his Projects. Alſo the Projectors laſt Will and Teſtament, with an Epitaph to his memory. By T. <hi>Brugis,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>Experto mihi credite.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Hearne, featuring a fleur-de-lis (McKerrow 251)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.H.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Lawrence Chapman,</hi> and <hi>William Cooke,</hi> at their ſhops in <hi>Holborne.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:2"/>
            <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, before thou peruſe my Booke give me leave to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe thee, that in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe, I doe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeke to defame any perſon of any degree whatſoever, nor intend I to ayme at the credit of any; but if any man finde himſelfe touched with any thing herein mentioned, let him make his beſt uſe of it for my part I ſhall onely deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale and diſcover ſuch abuſes as have crept into this Kingdome, which all his Majeſties Subjects with a longing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire do expect a reformation of, and God be thanked have already ſeene ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory events. Moreover, I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:56762:3"/> deſire thy favorable cenſure of this my Book, wherein thou ſhalt not find any refined lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or eloquent ſtile (for indeed the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject deſerved it not) but a plaine way fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as neere as I could for every mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, elſe would they want the ſport and content which I hope they will hereby reap, wherin they ſhall find nothing but what I have found my ſelfe by experience; And for the maintaining of the credit hereof, I muſt tell you that the copy lying by me this many yeeres (not with any intent ever to print it) did yeeld occaſion to divers of my friends to extract copies for themſelves; and moreover, the abſence of it from my hands for almoſt two yeares hath yeelded the like opportunity to divers others unknowne to me, whereby many copies (onely altered in ſome few words, have been lately by earneſt endevours ſought to be publiſhed for their owne Workes; This is all I can deſire, which if granted will ſtrongly oblige me to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate my labours to thy content, and my ſelfe thy profeſſed ſervant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="mock_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:3"/>
            <head>To the moſt Illuſtrious the luſticke Lanſgrave of <hi>Latmos</hi> the man in the Moone.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO thee (the moſt imaginary Sire)</l>
               <l>Of each tranſcendent wit, and Engine maker,</l>
               <l>The Ixion that firſt filcht Aethaeriall fire,</l>
               <l>And every new Inventions chiefe creator,</l>
               <l>The Moones Surveyor of her Workes, or rather</l>
               <l>Her Inſtructor, and our <hi>Projectors</hi> Father.</l>
               <l>J give thee here to know what er'ſt befell,</l>
               <l>The childe whom heretofore thou didſt beget,</l>
               <l>He that by Lines and Screwes would needes compell</l>
               <l>The Sun to mend his pace when he was ſet,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to reade this lamentable ſtory,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wit can gallop faſter then <hi>Iohn Dory.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>With the next Rundlet of his highneſſe Claret,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be this convey'd, and Ile be thankfull for it.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="lampoon">
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56762:4"/>
            <head>THE PROIECTOR, and his PROIECTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I firſt hapned upon this Subject, I ſcarce durſt venture the publiſhing of any thing concerning it, leſt I might be thought to touch at the credit and reputation of ſome perſons, whoſe worths are ſufficiently known unto the World, that although (by reaſon of the large pretences and fawning flatteries of Projectors) they have beene importuned in ſome ſort to countenance them, yet never have they beene confirmed in their good opinions and commendations. Let this therefore be apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie ſufficient for my ſelfe, that I intend not herein to touch the credit or reputation of any particular man, knowing, that <hi>Saepe à Principibus magna ruina venit.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Libelling will I ſeek to diſparage Arts or Artiſts (which ever were commendable in themſelves.) Neither will I diſpute what kind of government might ſeem moſt fit and convenient in generall: nor preſume to diſtinguiſh what regularity and order is moſt compliable with any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56762:5"/> particular kingdome, I perceive my ſelfe happy in being ignorant of ſuch tranſcendent learning: but I will onely aime at, &amp; denote certain abuſes inſerted into this peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and (in government) unparalleld Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>My ſubject therefore which I have found out, is ſo farre unworthy to be imployment for any ſolid capacity, that I had rather (if <hi>Hipponax</hi> (that never did any thing but what procured much laughter) were alive) to take this in hand, that he might be painted forth in his right coulours.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Projector,</hi> as farre as I can finde, never had genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſſe it were that he was begot on a faire Faggot pile, betweene the man in the Moone, and <hi>Tom Lancaſters</hi> Laundreſſe; ſome call him buſineſſe, but his moſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved name is <hi>Projector,</hi> a creature that never ſtayed his full time of hatching, but got out with the ſhell on his head, and ſo runne to Court, where he hath moſt ſeriouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed his time in Court ſuits, as in the ſequell of this ſtory I ſhall more at large decipher him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore I ſhall tell you what a <hi>Projector</hi> is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how he did become a <hi>Projector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how many profeſſions he left to become a <hi>Projector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, what ſucceſſe attended his new-found myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the ſingular good and benefit of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of this Realme, and the everlaſting memory of ſo profitable a Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, his death and free diſpoſall of all his goods and chattels, by his laſt Will and Teſtament to his ſucceſſors, and laſtly his Epitaph.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:56762:5"/>
               <head>What a Projector is.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Projector</hi> is derived from the Latine, and ſignifies a man of a good forecaſt, he is alſo ſaid to be a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Court ſuites, an Inventor and deviſor of new things, and a pretended reformer of the old, which goe commonly by the name of <hi>Projects,</hi> provided that they had no other beginning or former Invention; for if they bee received, renewed, or reported upon any record, they cannot come truely within the compaſſe of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But verily hee is the very Corne-cutter of the age wherein he lives, and hath a notable fault in the unſteadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his hand, by reaſon whereof he doth often thruſt his knife into the tender parts of a Common-wealth, to the very quicke, and never leaves untill he have brought out the very Coare of their purſes: he imployes all his time, labour, ſtudy, and experience onely to ſearch out the abuſes of every Place, Profeſſion, and Myſtery whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, next his greateſt ſtudy is to propoſe the faire outſide of a reformation, and this he begins with a Petition to his Majeſtie, with ſuch mighty pretences of enriching
<pb facs="tcp:56762:6"/> the Kingdome, that he dares moſt impudently to affirme that it ſhall bring to his Majeſtie, his Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for ever many thouſands yearely; yea, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for all the poore people of the Realme (which how well all theſe late <hi>Projects</hi> have effected, I leave to judicious cenſure;) next comes a reference where he ſtill averres what he in his Petition propoſed, and thus by his large offers, and mediation of friends to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees he obtaines a ſlight approbation enough onely to procure a <hi>Patent,</hi> then he thinkes the worlds his owne, and then muſt there be an Office erected, <hi>wherby his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, his Heires and Succeſſors ſhall receive wonderfll benefts, by augmenting his yearly Revenues, cuſtomes, and impoſts, and the Common-wealth exceeding great good and profit, and many thouſands of poore people at the leaſt ſhall finde ſufficient im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the iſſues proceeding of theſe his paines and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour (which he pretends to be onely for the good of his Countrey, <hi>himſelfe not getting by it one farthing</hi>) are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called or knowne by the name of <hi>Projects,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Author that invented and deviſe them, to which hee gives divers names, ſuch as their fancies beſt ſerved; the better to gull the ignorant, one whereof is called <hi>Heuretica,</hi> and that is an Art or Invention tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching how to deviſe new, and to reforme old, and is the firſt and chiefeſt of all, and as the <hi>primum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile;</hi> Likewiſe they give them other termes of Art as <hi>litterall Inventions, and Mechanick Inventions,</hi> a litterall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention is of <hi>Logicke, Rhethoricke, Grammer, the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Sciences,</hi> and writing all which they ſay were only <hi>Projects;</hi> A Mechanick Invention is the art of the <hi>Projector
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56762:6"/> which by effectuall Inſtruments and meanes bringeth forth, ſome new viſible Worke,</hi> pretended <hi>good and profitable to the Common-wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hitherto they adde the Myſtery of Printing, Shipping, the Art of Grinding, Building, making of Salt, Allomes, Coppers, Salt-peter, Felt-making, Sadlers, Carts, Ploughes, Harrowes, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they dare moſt impudently to affirme that all Arts, Trades, Crafts, Sciences, Myſteries, Occupations, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Deviſes, and ſlights whatſoever, were meerely <hi>Projects,</hi> in reſpect of the Authors that deviſed them, whom they will needes have (to uphold their owne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits) to be <hi>Projectors,</hi> and yet they pretend to mend all theſe, and to make them both more beneficiall, and more ſerviceable; likewiſe they will tell you that the firſt Diſcoveries of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> by <hi>Columbus, Magellane,</hi> and <hi>Drake,</hi> were <hi>Projects,</hi> ſeeking thereby to bring into their ranke of <hi>Projectors,</hi> three ſuch Ingenious, Noble, and Venturous perſons, And thus they gull the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by making many faire promiſes of wealth to fall upon them on a ſodaine, telling them that the Peſtle and Morter were good Primitive inventions, but the Water-Mill, Hand-mill, and Wind-mill, were derivative from them by a <hi>Projector,</hi> and much better, yet he will have another ſhall farre paſſe all theſe, and that he calls a <hi>Plegnicke Engine,</hi> which ſhall not onely grinde Corne as the Mills, but ſhall alſo ſerve to blow the Bellowes to any Furnace, and never ſtand ſtill as the Milles doe, but be in perpetuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Smithes ordinary Bellowes are nought, a ſcurvie <hi>Primitive Invention,</hi> hee hath a <hi>Derivative</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56762:7"/> Invention worth a hundred of them, more handſomly and ſtrongly made, which ſhall blow forth not onely cold wind, but alſo flames of fire, water, and duſt, at the ſame time, and at the ſame hole. And theſe are the chiefe heads of <hi>Projecting.</hi> Next I will ſhew you what they pretend the nature of every <hi>Project</hi> (of their deviſing) to be: to which I will adde the faults liable, and never wanting in them.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, they make every <hi>Project</hi> to be of two degrees, the leſſer and the greater; and each degree is three-fold. The leſſer vertues of every <hi>Project</hi> are, Equi-ſufficiency, Equi-cheapneſſe, Equi-excellency; but the greater are, more ſufficient, more cheape, more excellent: This is the chiefe Axel-tree that upholds and carries all <hi>Projects;</hi> for all <hi>Projectors</hi> do pretend the three laſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry new invention.</p>
               <p>But now let us come to the faults, which although they are but three, yet I beleeve they will be found more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently than the three Vertues; and theſe are leſſe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, leſſe cheapneſſe, and leſſe excellencie. The greater faults are alſo three, that is, inſufficiency, exceeding dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and exceeding baſeneſſe, uglineſſe, or ilfavoured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and of theſe I muſt confeſſe I never ſaw any <hi>Project</hi> that had not the moſt part, if not all. Theſe faults ſhall be compared to the vertues, when we come to ſpeak of the ſucceſſe that attended theſe new found Miſteries.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are willing to deale in any theſe new <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> either by being <hi>Patentees,</hi> Clerks of the <hi>Patent,</hi> Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors of the <hi>Workes,</hi> by buying <hi>Shares, Halfe Shares,</hi> or <hi>Quarter parts, &amp;c.</hi> muſt be ſure to have their purſe well li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for they ſhall be at continuall expence, and it may be never receive farthing profit. As firſt, their ſhare may coſt a hundred or two hundred pounds, the uſe of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56762:7"/> is loſt, and yet they ſhall be aſſeſſed to pay for every <hi>Full Part</hi> that coſts an hundred pounds, ten or 12 pounds once or twice a yeare, towards the erecting the <hi>Works,</hi> and propagating the buſineſſe. And thus they live in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about fourteene yeares (the uſuall limit for <hi>Patents</hi> in that kind) and if it chance to hold out ſo long, in any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood then it comes to his Majeſty. But they ſeldom laſt to that, for the State perceiving their fooleries, and that they can never accompliſh the thouſand part of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and the commonwealths expectation, calls in their <hi>Patents,</hi> leaving the <hi>Projector</hi> far ingaged to his friends, by bringing them into ſuch a deale of trouble and expence to no purpoſe, by his faire promiſes and perſwaſions, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſome have all their eſtate (which though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps but mean, yet might have honeſtly maintained them) layd at the ſtake, relying onely on the <hi>Projectors</hi> vain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; who deales much like the <hi>Turkiſh Alcharon,</hi> that if they will obey the Lawes and Decrees of their great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> they ſhall have after their deaths brave gardens, pleaſant fountaines, and Wenches with great eyes. Even thus they play their part, promiſing thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands yearely to them that will lay downe any money to propagate a new invention: and the more to delude their Creditors, they will upon the leaſt objection or miſlike, be preſently ready (like ſome ſects of Hereticks) to prove their profeſſion by Scripture to be right and ſtraight, and call all Artificers <hi>Projectors,</hi> and all arts and ſciences <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> which are nothing in effect but the vain iſſues of idle braines. Thoſe (as I told you) that would deal in any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> muſt be ſure to have in readineſſe good bags of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: for all your <hi>Projectors</hi> hold this as a generall maxim, <hi>That it is the wiſeſt, ſafeſt, and moſt credible courſe for a</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56762:8"/> 
                  <hi>not to aske under hand, whereby he ſhall be driven to repaire to them againe the ſecond time, but rather at the firſt let him agree for more money, and not for leſſe then will ſerve the turne towards his expences in trials,</hi> and hereof every Sharer <hi>muſt beare pay, defray and diſcharge his part equally with the parties individent.</hi> And therefore they tell their Vndertakers, that <hi>they muſt expect ſome loſſe in the triall of new buſineſſes, be the</hi> Projector <hi>never ſo perfect in his</hi> Theoricke, <hi>for though he endevours never ſo much to give his Workmen true and perfect directions, and inſtruct his Artificers never ſo carefully, yet they will often faile, and erre in their Worke, by which meanes the Inſtrument being experimented, and put to triall, becommeth inſufficient for the appointed uſe, and many times</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Projector may faile himſelfe in ſome one point, for which there is no helpe, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to redreſſe and amend the fault in the Inſtrument, or elſe to make a new Inſtrument in the others ſtead, neither of which can be done without further charge;</hi> and this muſt the Sharers diſburſe, and yet there muſt be (as they call it) an <hi>annuall charge,</hi> which is an <hi>aſſeſsing of every Sharer from time to time upon occaſion, for monies to maintaine, repaire, and continue the ſaid primary Inſtruments belonging to the ſaid new buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, after the firſt Plantation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the errours, ſome the <hi>Projector</hi> (to ſave himſelf) layes on the Workmen, the Creditors on the <hi>Projector,</hi> ſo that after much trouble, paines, vexation, and charges, and daily expectation of the great ſummes which would <hi>ariſe and acrew</hi> thereby, doing their utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours both by money and friends, to <hi>ſet forward, further and advance this admirable Worke,</hi> have in the end, juſt their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for their paines, and are glad to ſit downe by the loſſe, becauſe either the <hi>Projector</hi> hath ſhewed them a faire
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56762:8"/> paire of heeles (as moſt of them doe) or elſe not worth one groat whereby to give them the leaſt ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How he became a Projector.</head>
               <p>HE became a <hi>Projector</hi> in this ſort, and upon this very occaſion following. Feeling a conſumptive weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his Shop and Warehouſe, and continuall moſt terrible Convulſions in his Counterbox, he began moſt grievouſly to complaine, and cry out of the Collick, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly expecting an Eruption; hereupon he day by day imployes himſelfe in making a moſt ſtrict ſcrutiny and review into his Shopbooks, as well for debtors ſolvent, as inſolvent, he moſt diligently compares his <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> together, and vowes to ſpare no man whom the Law puts into his hand, at length to his comfort he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately lights upon a debt of his Cozen at Court, <hi>For ſuch a piece of Stuffe, ſo much:</hi> this makes him; and although hee once thought it a very deſperate debt, yet now hee will ſpend ſome time in adventuring his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the triall of procuring it; whereupon he makes many viſits at Court, thinking with himſelf that perhaps his kinſman may have ſo much good nature remaine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56762:9"/> in him, as to take ſome occaſion to ſpeake of it himſelfe: but his Couſine was crafty enough to worke beſt for his owne advantage, and ſo from time to time put him off with other diſcourſe. But at laſt miſtruſting what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was, and that all his cunning could not rid him of this <hi>Hinchman,</hi> that neither the ſhewing of the Privy lodgings, nor a place for his ſhe couſin at a Maſque, nor the ſending of Veniſon twice in a ſeaſon, nor the bottle of the Kings wine, nor the Court tart, nor all the Court complements and proteſtations could once procure him to grant longer day; that neither the Winter journies, nor the Summer progreſſe could induce him to forget it, or at leaſt to leave his opportunity, hee reſolved the next time hee came to give him ſome ſatisfaction, and therefore upon his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed time of viſitation, knowing his place and poſture, found him waiting his comming out, and there with a moſt court nod he beckned him to come forward, and thus he accoſted him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Couſin, I have conſidered of your more than ordinary frequent viſitations, which I conceive to ariſe from that little matter of debt that is betwixt us. You know we are ſeldome counted monied men, and I proteſt I have not wherewithall to ſatisfie your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation for the preſent; but I had thought that ſo many curteſies might have countervailed ſo ſmall a matter, and have made you a little more reſpective. Yet that I may in ſome ſort ſatisfie you I will put you in the way that ſhall make you for ever, and bee worth no leſſe than thouſands yearely into your purſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This made the Citiſen ſtart, with ſuch a kind of altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if joy and feare had ſtrove together within him: the onely naming of riches encreaſed joy, when on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den a feare poſſeſſed him, leſt it might not be true which he heard. But expelling this extaſie, he attended the ſequel
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56762:9"/> of the ſtory in this manner,) <hi>The buſineſſe I have already very well conſidered and make no queſtion, but I ſhall ſuddenly procure a</hi> Patent of Priviledge <hi>from his Majeſtie to engroſſe it ſolely to my ſelfe for I thinke it will ſcarce come to more then a Copy-hold</hi> Project, <hi>which muſt not exceed ten thouſand pounds</hi> per annum; <hi>for if it ſhould exceed that, then it were a royall Invention, and due onely to his Majeſtie. And I can aſſure you, if ever there were an ingenuous Art conſiſting of heate without the ſight of fire and ſmoake, for all mens uſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented queſtionleſſe this is the ſame, or elſe it is not to be found upon the earth: but ſurely (Cozen) till our Times Warres, and Barbarity have never ſuffered ſo noble an Invention to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare; or if at any time there hath beene any ſuch Invention, it lyeth antiquated, and now is revived; and this is a kinde of new deviſed Furnace or Kilne, which ſhall Roaſt, bake, and Boyle, and ſtarch Cloathes, dry Mault, Hoppes, Wheate, Oates, Felts, or any other thing, witbout ſight of fire or touch of ſmoak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, and that without danger of fiering, for they are ſo perfectly made and framed, that they cannot take fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, they are made to divert ſmoake, the chiefe enemie to mans health, and particularly to his eyes, his head, his heart, and lungs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, they doe neatly and ſweetly roaſt our meat, that no vapour or fume can come neare unto it, which is both a neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and a ſingular ſafety; no Sout falleth here into the Pottage, nor fat into the fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly theſe Kilnes and Furnaces ſhall dry Mault more conſtantly in every part of the Kilne, becauſe the ſweet heate without ſmoake is diſperſed proportionably into all parts at once, ſo that all the Mault ſhall bee dryed alike, and ſo your Sixe ſhillings Beare ſhall bee as ſtrong as tenne ſhillings Beare made of ordinary dryed Mault,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56762:10"/> and the reaſon is partly beoauſe the old ſmoaky kilnes leave many cornes undryed, and partly, becauſe the ſmoake piercing through the wet Mault, and there finding reſiſtance maketh an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deepe and ſtrong impreſsion into the very body and centre of the Mault, and there drieth, infecteth, and conſumeth the very ſpirit (which is a kind of Balſamicall ſalt) and radicall moiſture, juice, and ſubſtance of the Mault.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiftly, they dry Hoppes ſweetly without ſmoake, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Flower in its owne nature, which the ſmoaky Kilnes doe deſtroy, ſo Hoppes which are but a Flower and of tender parts by the ſmoaky drying Kilnes doe looſe the beſt of their radicall moiſture, and moſt of their Balſamicall ſpirit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in a manner only their fixt Salt together with their excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious dead ſubſtance, and the Salt infection of the ſmoake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtly, they dry black or ſmotty Wheat, Oates, or any other graine, or fiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly, they ſhall ſave much fewell as one fourth part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly, they will dry any thing that needs drying without the leaſt touch of ſmoake, ſo that it may be termed an Invention, or rather a new and marveilous Art, to all men admirably uſefull, injurious to none: moreover mans health (without which Honour, Fame, Riches, Friends, and Life it ſelfe ſeemes but troubleſome and noiſome) cannot be long conſerved in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eſtate, or once loſt be well recovered without this invention, as the properties thereof doe clearly, and Philoſophically, and Experimentally from our owne very ſences demonſtrate. Of this rare invention I had obtained a grant for the ſole uſe of our late Soveraigne King</hi> James, <hi>but before his Letters could be made Patents, and paſſe the ordinary Offices of this Kingdome our peaceable King departed this life, and ſo by the diſturbance of cruell fortune I was hindred from proſecuting my good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, but notwithſtanding all theſe my miſfortunes, croſſes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56762:10"/> and loſſes in this world, I have againe adventured to publiſh my Workes, and petition his Majeſtie for his Letters Patents of Priviledge for the ſole uſing, and licenſing of this ſaid Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the goodneſſe and ſingularity thereof I will ſpeake no more, for the workes themſelves wilbe Vocall, and I ſhall make it appeare to be ſo beneficiall, and profitable to my countrey and commonwealth, that it ſhall bring to the Kings Majeſtie his Heires and Succeſſors yearly, many thouſands, with the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many thouſands of poore people; And Couzen if you can but procure one thing, you make your ſelfe and me for ever, that is, I would have you to take up ſome ſtore of money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you knew there muſt be ſome few Fees ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſervants and Clarkes, and that we may be able to make our trialls for one part of the Organicke meanes of a Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke is procuring, now the procuring meanes is money to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended and diſburſed in charges, for it is the inſtrument of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and meane of Meanes, procuring all other inſtruments and meanes meerely operative, and when once they are procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and provided by it, it meaſureth their worth and valuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and theſe moneys I call primary and annuall; the primary moneyes are ſuch as I would have you procure to be diſburſed about the firſt foundation, erection, and ſetting up my new buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in ſome one convenient place, whereby my work-houſe may be furniſhed with all Permanent and Tranſient Tooles, and Instruments; Tranſient Tooles are all kind of Fewell, and Oare, which ſerve but once, but Permanent Tooles are ſuch as ſerve divers times as are the ſeverall ſolid hand Tooles or other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments uſed by any kind of trade, likewiſe it wilbe requiſite to build Models both Saperficiall, Reall, Directionall, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, which cannot be done but with greate charge; as for the annuall diſburſments the ſharers ſhall expend equally, and that you may have ſuch ſatisfaction as you expect by my diſcourſe I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56762:11"/> ſhall not thinke it ſufficient to offer you a ſhare, but am willing to joyne you</hi> Patentee <hi>with me; and thus you may be ſure, that by this meanes we ſhall both increaſe our eſtates, and advance our names.</hi> He tels him moreover, <hi>that ſuch and ſo potent are his friends, that he ſhould take it as a great treſpaſſe to his reputation, once to queſtion the obtaining of his ſuit;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome urgent occaſion, hee could not ſpend ſo much time in this Diſcourſe, as he deſired, nor utter his minde ſo fully to him, as he could wiſh he might, but if his occaſions would permit him to give him a meeting, any day in the long Gallery that reaches over the middle Temple towards the water ſide, or under the Temple trees, he would moſt willingly imbrace that opportunity, where he would borrow more time to ſpend about this buſineſſe, to his greater and more fuller ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Solemne leave is taken on both ſides, the Citizen goes home almoſt extaſied, ſcarce feeling the ground hee went on, he was ſo taken with his Cozens <hi>Project:</hi> well, he immediately goes home, takes up all the money he poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly can, and ſeekes all that he can by friends and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to get into ſome Pariſh Office, whereby hee may come to have the ſtock thereof in his cuſtody: his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-houſe is redeemed, and becauſe it ſeemes too little, and hath no good forefront, nor proſpect from his <hi>Balcone,</hi> therefore there muſt be laid out in building thrice as much as the Fee-ſimple of all when it is finiſhed will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford; and laſt of all he vowes to forſake the plaine path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of all Trades, Profeſſions, and Myſteries whatſoever, and places more faith in a <hi>Project,</hi> then in all the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of his own Trading, for by this he thinks to raiſe his fortunes on a ſodaine: but take it for a generall rule, when a Citizen turnes <hi>Projector,</hi> he hath the very Tokens
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56762:11"/> of the wonderfull cracke upon him, and ſo out of all hope of recovery although he may linger on.</p>
               <p>After he had long beat his brains about this buſines, he calls to minde a cunning crafty Scriviner, the very <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verint</hi> of his age, and one who had lived long in the City, and knew all their trickes to a haire; this man had alſo a great deſire to become rich on a ſodaine; him he meetes at the Ship behinde the Old Exchange, and there prepares him for his purpoſe, and the next morning he appointed to come to the Scriveners houſe, to know his opinion upon conſideration of the buſineſſe; which accordingly hee did, and ſound him in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber chopping up a few prayers (as one that was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to trouble <hi>God Almightie</hi> too much) and withall (being a man that could rather do two things at once, then loſe any minute of time) hee was croſſe-gartering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, where without the leaſt diſturbance of his devotion, hee prayes and diſcourſes of the buſineſſe all at a breath, and commends much the courſe hee intended, ſeriouſly vowing to further and aide him all hee could or might, which hee delivered with a kinde of familiar wringing him by the hand, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to inſinuate his meaning, as unto his Share. Hereupon they walke along to the Taverne to drinke their mornings draught, good compliance is on both ſides, and the Scrivener (as the common uſe and practiſe of them is) was ever more ready in promiſing, then the other in propounding, inſomuch that an unſpeakeable and inſeparable amity was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded betweene them, and ſo for that time they parted.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56762:12"/>
               <p>Next he remembers a grave Counſellour, one whom few Clients gave leiſure enough to think on the forme of drawing the conveyances and aſſignments of the ſhares, halfe parts, and deputations of Shires, beſides an intimate friend of his, a learned man both in Philoſophy and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; he was further aſſured of ſome friends in the Weſt Country, moſt <hi>Pragmaticall</hi> for new Inventions, who were buſied in their <hi>Patents</hi> for extractions, and ſeparations of Minerals, and Mettalls, by new invented meanes, ſome others alſo from the Allome Workes, who played the like trickes of <hi>Leger-de-Maine,</hi> with their Vndertakers, that if they and their Clearks can agree in their accounts they are like to make their dealers ſcarce able to retaine their Vrine, if they fall not into uncurable ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury.</p>
               <p>Then hee goes to an old Vſurer, one whom he knew alwayes to be ſtored with plenty of <hi>Plutoes Corn,</hi> and tels him that he is likely to obtaine <hi>a Patent of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from his Majeſtie, to erect certaine new</hi> Projects <hi>in his Highneſſe Realmes of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales: and becauſe he wants ſome ſmall matter to expend in trials, he deſires him to let him have ſo much, and he will morgage him <hi>a full part of the cleare Profits ariſing and acrewing thereby.</hi> The Vſurer ſeeing him gravely clad, and withall, having knowne him before for a man ſufficient (as he imagined) was content, ſo as he had his deſire, and the other thought he could not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter place his money,</p>
               <p>Next he goes to a rich Widdow of his familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and ſhewes her whole bagges of Silver, and tels her that if ſhe would joyne in a bargaine with him, that he could now have, it would make them both for ever;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56762:12"/> the Widdow, when ſhe had heard on his tale, began al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to leape for joy, and her fingers itched to be telling out the money, that ſhe ſhould get yearely by her ſhare, and therefore with much dexterity diſpatched him, and thus he was througly provided towards his <hi>fundamentall expences.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How many Profeſsions he left to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Projector.</head>
               <p>NExt let me ſhew you how many Trades, Functions, and Occupations he left to become a <hi>Projector,</hi> for if he be a decay'd Merchant, this Profeſſion may put him in hope of procuring a Protection, if an unpractiſed Lawyer, it may be a meanes to draw good ſtore of Clients to his Chamber, if an old caſt <hi>Auditor,</hi> it may finde him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment enough to caſt and calculate how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands yearely every Sharers part comes to in the conception of any theſe new <hi>Projects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, the Lawyers were found exceeding forward, and and becauſe ſome of them had few Clients, and leſſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, they would mend the matter by getting the grant of a fift Terme.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Merchant had too long truſted to <hi>Byling ſleyes</hi> Bookes, and finding ſmall profit thereby, hee haſtens to the Court to preſent his ſuite, and expect the ſucceſſe of new Inventions.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56762:13"/>
               <p>Thirdly, the Fiſhmongers if it were not for a poore <hi>Lent,</hi> now almoſt loſt for want of cuſtome, had but an ill yeare made up of Frydayes and Saturdayes, (which ſcarce would bee neither, if it were not for ſome, who being weary with glutting themſelves with Fleſh, did not deſire Fiſh for varieties ſake) therefore they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to goe to the Weſterne Seas, where a certaine <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector</hi> will finde imployment for them, and bring to this Kingdome forty Millions of pounds yearely.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Baker miſlikes his Oven utterly, and ſeekes to reforme it, which done, hee gets a <hi>Patent of Priviledge,</hi> that none may doe it but himſefe; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee found not imployment ſufficient to maintaine himſelf in this Kingdome, therfore they report he is gone into <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, the Brewer, poore melancholy man, cannot tell what to ſay to the buſineſſe, but he findes Mault very deare, and never worſe, which he conceives to proceed from the new Kilnes, &amp; his cuſtomers cry out on him for hopping too much: wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is reſolved to Petition his Majeſtie, that the new <hi>Project</hi> of Kilnes may be ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and likewiſe the <hi>Patent</hi> of incorporating Maulſters, and then hee is verily perſwaded he ſhall afford us better Beere, and at an eaſier rate.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, the Mettle-men, Braſiers, Cutlers, Smithes, Plummers, and the Myſterie of Alchimiſts, perceiving Trading begin to be very ſcarce in <hi>London,</hi> are all reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved very ſpeedily to repaire to the Forreſt a Deane.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, next came the whole Rabble of poor Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes Clerkes, who were the chiefe upholders (and had for the moſt part beene there bred up) of the three-peny Ordinary in <hi>Warwicke-lane,</hi> where they aſcend their dining
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56762:13"/> roome with a Ladder, which (their dyet being once ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in) was moſt ceremoniouſly taken away.</p>
               <p>And theſe kinde of people having left their aforeſaid Profeſſions, had a great mind to become rich on a ſudden, and therefore they quickly ſought out our former Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, who as I ſhewed you before was already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a moſt excellent proficient as any of his time; here he makes them begin (as he had formerly done) firſt with their <hi>accidence,</hi> which is <hi>Topliffes</hi> notes, then to their Grammar which is <hi>Pheltons</hi> Bookes, and thus they have good method for what they undertake. Theſe are they who reſpect not the bredth of the Church doore, but bend all their endeavours, and imploy all their wits to be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the profundity, and meaſuring the circumference of other mens purſes, nay, there ſhall not a trade, profeſſion, myſterie, place, or office have a jadiſh tricke more than ordnary, but they will whip the bawd, and preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a generall reformation. Moreover, theſe poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Tradeſmen, and the aforeſaid ragged regiment of diſcontented Clerkes, will open the whole ſecrets of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profeſſion; they will tell you what a quantity of Gum and Coperas the whole office ſpends in a yeare, and what ſtore of calve-skins paſſe through their hands every terme.</p>
               <p n="8">8 I had almoſt forgot thoſe that were to have had the firſt place in regard of their priority in <hi>Projects,</hi> and theſe are your eminent Citizens of Blackfryers, <hi>Engliſh Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermakers, Dutch Iewellers, Scotch Taylors, and French Shoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers,</hi> with all their forraine forces, who are like to enjoy their ancient priviledges without moleſtation or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of any kinde.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The Miller likewiſe had almoſt been ſlipt over, yet hee cannot fadge with his old Mill, it grindes not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56762:14"/> well, nor faſt enough he cannot grow rich with it quickly enough, therefore he will have a horſe-wind-water-mill, and engroſſe it to himſelfe. Theſe and many more might be rehearſed, but I will give but a touch upon every one of them, whereby you may judge of the whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What ſucceſſe attended his new found Myſteries, to the ſingular comfort of the Common-wealth, and the everlaſting memory of ſo profitable a Profeſsion.</head>
               <p>THis Cozen of ours being ſo plentifully furniſhed, ſet them all on Worke, every one in his ſeverall Function and Profeſſion, wherein they laboured with much willingneſſe and dexterity, that every one brought him ſo great variety of Art and Workemanſhip, that he tooke upon him to ſupply all manner of Courtiers with theſe kinde of commodities.</p>
               <p>Then he cals all his Aſſociates (being bold Britaines) to a publique aſſembly, drils them in the Garden, and they make their ſet battels under the Trees in the new Walks, which piece of ground was liſted in, and levelled for the ſame purpoſe; and here he began to ſhew them how eaſie a matter it was for them to ſtrip themſelves of their meane eſtate and condition, whereto they were collapſed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56762:14"/> and on a ſodaine become mighty <hi>Projectors,</hi> ſome ſhould be Officers of ſuperintendency, ſome generall Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of reformation, others Diſpenſers of Law terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing penalties, and in generall all moſt deare and naturall <hi>Patrons</hi> &amp; <hi>Patricions</hi> of their mother country, telling them alſo <hi>how eaſie theſe wayes would ſeeme to them if the ingenuous reaſons were once looked into, that there will accrew much joy and comfort unto them when they ſhall ſee the reaſons of ſo Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall profit, or profitable Philoſophy; as on the other ſide</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I hold theſe moſt miſerable men, or rather images, or Cyphers of men, then very men indeed, who imploy their buſie time and care in idleneſſe, vaine Paſtimes, long ſleepes, &amp;c. as though they had no more time then might be well ſpent in the exalting of vertue, ſupplanting of vice, and profiting their countrey, friends, and conſanguinity, but you onely are to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and accounted happy, who uſe your time (being ſo great a treaſure) in perfecting ſuch good Workes, and rare Inventions as are both honeſt and profitable to whole Nations, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to our owne Kingdome, who keepe warre againſt ignorance that knoweth no vertue, honeſty nor duty, and therfore meaneth no truth; for our parts (let malicious envie detract never ſo much) yet after Ages ſhall ſay, that we meant really and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly, and our endeavours aimed at ſuch ſubſtantiall markes as containe the honour, fame, and perpetuall memory of our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigne, and his Subjects health, profit, and pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe men thus tickled in the head thought that they had certainely now, and never till now found out the true way of thriving, protection, and good forecaſt, whereupon they all agreed, that this was the onely way to become ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich, that ever was or could be diſcovered; and ſo from thenceforth (after the manner of their maſter) they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56762:15"/> tooke upon them the name of <hi>Projectors,</hi> men of the beſt forecaſt, utterly diſclaiming all their former Trades, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Arts, Sciences, Myſteries, Crafts, and Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to all intents and purpoſes whatſoever.</p>
               <p>It would doe you good to heare the whole packe of theſe together, they are ſo excellent both for ſent and cry, and becauſe you ſhall ſee what varieties of <hi>Projects</hi> they daily brought in, I will endeavour to relate ſome of them to you, whereof ſome have failed long ſince, and are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboliſh'd, others make a faire ſhew for the preſent, but are very likely to come to the ſame paſſe the former have done; and by theſe that I will deſcribe you may judge what the reſt are like to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Projects.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe good old Scriviner hee would needs have a Monopoly, were it but the ſole engroſſing of all Loveletters in Proſe and Verſe in theſe his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 The Lawyers had a great mind to have foyſted in a fift Terme, and have encreaſed the multiplication of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers according to the augmentation of ſuites of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age above the former.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The officer on the Banke ſide, beſide certaine ſmall impoſitions deviſed how to entitle the chiefe Butler to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56762:15"/> the ſole Licenſing of all Liters and ſmall Veſſels for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying and recarrying of all Merchandiſes whatſoever within the River of Thames.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>Engineer</hi> would drive backe the Ocean, and make firme land, not doubting but by that and certaine hidden Treaſure, or Treaſure Trover elſewhere whereof he had notice, the world ſhould take more notice of him very ſhortly.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Miller had invented a new Milne to grinde Corne, and becauſe the old Windmill had not onely his Sailes mounted in the Wind, but alſo all the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke of the Milne, by which meanes it is ſubject to bee blowne downe with ſtormes; hee therefore will have a <hi>Plegnicke</hi> Windmill to ſtand firme on the ground without any hazzard or danger of blowing downe; and as the old Milne hath his croſſe Sailes to be haled, and turned to the Wind, this Milne ſhall have Sayles lye round on the top of the houſe, alwayes ready for all Winds; it ſhall grinde with three or four pair of Stones at once, and three or foure times as much Meale in one houre; and of theſe he would have five ſorts; the firſt was called a <hi>Horſewin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it moved with the Horſe and Wind; the ſecond was a <hi>Horſewater,</hi> becauſe it went by Horſe, and Water; the third a <hi>Windwater,</hi> becauſe it went by Wind and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the fourth a <hi>Horſwinwater,</hi> moved with Horſe, winde, and Water together; the fifth a <hi>Water Plegnicke</hi> which ſhould move inviſibly under the water by the Water.</p>
               <p n="6">6 There is a <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> Metalorganicke, which chiefly by the meanes of <hi>Plegnicke</hi> Inſtruments ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth another new kinde of Water Milnes, Windmilnes, Horſe Milnes, and hand Milns for the grinding of Corn, Tanners Barke, Brazill, for the ſawing of Woodes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56762:16"/> making of Oyles, battering of Irons, and Coppers, and for Tuckeage and Fullage of Woollen cloth, or Yellow oyled Leathers, or for any other uſe or purpoſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that other Milnes ſerve for, and theſe are leſſe charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make, ſet up, keepe, and repaire, and yet more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and convenient then any other ſort of Milnes which be now in uſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7 There is a <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> of making an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall kinde of Water-Work for the abundant raiſing, and mounting of Water after an eaſier order then thoſe that are already uſed in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p n="8">8 There is <hi>another new Art and Invention</hi> for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of very effectuall and beneficiall Inſtruments of Fiſhing, as new kinde of <hi>Burces,</hi> new kinde of <hi>Nettage,</hi> and <hi>Bateage,</hi> by which new deviſed meanes, great abundance of Fiſh might be caught with farre leſſe charges, and in ſhorter time then by the ordinary Arts of Fiſhing.</p>
               <p n="9">9 There is another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> of making divers kindes of Houſe-hold moveables, as artificiall Doores, Windowes, Curtaines, Preſſes, Tables, Stooles, Bedſteads, Hangings, Cheſts, and divers other things, handſommer, and more convenient then heretofore is done by the ordinary way of other ſtuffe.</p>
               <p n="10">10 There is another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> by divers new exact Mechanike Artes, Myſteries, Wayes and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, to melt, make and worke Irons, Steeles, Leades, Tinnes, Coppers, Braſſes, and ſuch like; alſo all kinde of <hi>Metalick concoctions,</hi> as Sandmettals, Aſhemettals Ammels, and ſuch like; alſo all kinde of burnt Earthes, as Tyles, Pavingſtones, Brickes, and ſuch like, with Seacoale, Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coale, Earthcoale, and Bruſh Fewell, and this wayes hee could ſave in this Kingdome, three hundred and thirty thouſand pounds yeerely.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56762:16"/>
               <p n="11">11 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> is for the bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Fowle and Pullen, which he would have ſold, but at the rate of eight pence a couple, one with another, and would be worth (as he ſayes) in this Kingdome, yeerely foure hundred thouſand pounds.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> is to plant great ſtore of Fruit trees in this Kingdome, which would ariſe to twelve hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> is to ſuppreſſe halfe the Pigeon houſes, and Pigeons kept over Gates, Chambers, and other places for that purpoſe, whereby he would yeerely ſave in this Kingdome, ſo much Corne as is worth two Millions of pounds at the leaſt, which they deſtroy and ſpoyle.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Another by deſtroying all feathered Fowles, would ſave yeerely in this Realme as much Corne as is worth three Millions of pounds.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Another by deſtroying of Vermine, would ſave yearely the worth of five thouſand pound at the leaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides young Fawnes, Hawks, and Rabbets.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Another by a generall deſtroying of Rats, and Mice, would ſave yearely, in Bread, Cheeſe, Corne, and other things, foure hundred thouſand pounds at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>So that in theſe ſixe laſt <hi>Projects,</hi> he would ſave yearely in this Kingdome nine Millions, two hundred thouſand pounds, beſides the good that ſhould grow therby to the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> was deviſed and erected for the Inſtitution of Noblemen and Gentlemen, and all ingenuous men who will ſtrive to deſerve, called an Academy, but that was not the Inventors aime, for hee cared not how they profited, ſo his purſe might have ſome feeling.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56762:17"/>
               <p n="18">18 Another <hi>rare Art and Invention</hi> was put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the making of excellent good Barre Iron from the Iron Stone or Mine to the Barre without the help of a Furnace, and that with Small Coale; and in every Tun of Iron, whereas the old way of melting ſpent at the leaſt ſixe loads and a halfe of Charcoale, this way would ſpend in every Tunne but five loades of Small Coale.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> was to make and erect certain new Kilnes or Furnaces to dry Mault, Hops, waſht Wheat, Oats, Flaxe, Hempe, Barke, Felt, Fiſh, Wooll, and ſuch like without the touch of ſmoake, alſo with the ſelfe-ſame fire, and at the ſame time, will in a moſt perfect forme and equality of diſperſion of heate, roaſt, bake, boyle, or brew, dry linnen, ſtove, bathe, diſtill, and ſuch like things without the ſight of fire or annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſmoake.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Another <hi>new Art and Invention</hi> is deviſed by the Fulling Milner, which was a Woodden Horſe, that with Scrues and Deviſes ſhould travell further in a day by much then the <hi>Dromedaries,</hi> carry a farre greater burthen and I warrant you faſt much longer, and for profit hee is very reaſonable, for hee craves but one of the new Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things for every pound that all Brewers, Bakers, Carriers, Kidders, Maulſters, and others ſhall carry, or tranſport thereon from place to place through the Realmes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, and Ireland, and Dominion of Wales, toward the repairing of the crackt <hi>perricranion</hi> much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed in the ſtudy of this rariety, which for Art and Workmanſhip ſurpaſſeth any that ever was Invented of that ſort.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Another ſeeing Graine grow very deare, and mouthes daily increaſe, for a remedy Invented how to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56762:17"/> make good and perfect <hi>nutrimentall bread</hi> of Pompeons, Mellons and Cucumbers, and intended preſently to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Myſtery, unleſſe the Company of Bakers would make compoſition with him for the ſuppreſſion of the ſecret.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Another moſt rare and new Intendion was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve life by removing of any man from the cold into the warme, and from the warme into a more warmer cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, exceeding in heat as Nature ſhall more and more decay, and old age draw on, whereby to ſupply that with Art, wherein Nature faileth. A brave <hi>Project</hi> to make the life of man (by obſerving of this order, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sunne as he goes forward in age) to continue five times as long. An excellent <hi>Invention,</hi> certainely to foole the Fates, and a ſtratageme to overthrow the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Fabricke of the <hi>Pharmacopea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23 This puts me in minde of another, a very notable one, who pretended to lengthen life alſo by removing ill ſavours; And to this end his ingenuous <hi>Projecting</hi> braine deviſed that every man, and woman within the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhould imploy two boxes made very cloſe of Wood to keepe in the ſmell, and theſe muſt be removed with Carts every two dayes, and then brought againe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcharged, and cleanſed; and for theſe his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines, and charges, hee would have but a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Weeke of every houſe, onely the chiefeſt gaine he expected was out of that which he carried away, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee intended to make Saltpeter, and ſo furniſh the Realme extraordinarily with Gunpowder; this was not very well liked by the Goldfinders, for had it gone on, they muſt of neceſſity have turned Saltpetermen, becauſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56762:18"/> they know no other trade but what concerned ſuch ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buſineſſe.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Another <hi>new Invention</hi> was the ingroſſing of Soapemaking, which when all the Vndertakers were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beggered, they were glad to ſell to the Old Soape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers againe.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Another <hi>new Invention</hi> was to ſeale all the Butter that came into the Cities of <hi>London, Briſtow,</hi> or <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> pretending none but what was very good, and for every Firkin he engroſſed two pence.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Another <hi>moſt rare Invention</hi> was that becauſe Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is held unlawfull by the lawes of God and Man, and only connived at for tradings ſake, therfore he would have all Vſurers pay to the King twelve pence in every pound of money taken for Intereſt, ſo that out of the yeares uſe of one hundred pounds, his Majeſtie ſhould have eight ſhillings.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Another would have an halfepeny a joynt for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry joynt of Meat dreſt by any common Cooke, on a Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day or Saturday.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Another conſidering the great inconvenience to the City of <hi>London</hi> by the ſmoake of the Brickilns, would have a <hi>Patent</hi> to make them pay ſixepence in every thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Brickes.</p>
               <p>I could increaſe my booke to a greater Volume, if I ſhould name all the <hi>Projects</hi> which I have knowne, but becauſe I intend this booke for an houres recreation I will conclude with one more.</p>
               <p n="29">29 The next therefore comes the whole rabble of thredbare Clerkes, and bankerupt Tradeſmen, who having already diſcovered and laid open the abuſes, deciets, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56762:18"/> ſlights of all Offices, and Occupations fit for reformation, would now in all the haſte have an Office erected to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Aſſigners, create Regiſters, Surveyors, deputy Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors, Clerkes of the <hi>Patent,</hi> Maſters of the Workes, and the like, together with Clerkes of every ſeverall Shire the better to attend &amp; ſee to the reformation, and to gather up the yearely revenues, and returne them into the Office, and all this ſhould be for the eaſe and releife of the poore ſubject, and great revenues to his Majeſtie, his Heires, and Succeſſors.</p>
               <p n="32">32 Of this ragged regiment, the one had ſtolne an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of making an <hi>Engine</hi> with a <hi>Plegnicke Screw,</hi> for this ſervice of purpoſe, tenne whereof being plied with three able men a piece ſhould beat an Army of thirty thouſand armed men out of the field; but ſayes he, when it hath kill'd a whole Army of men, and they very thicke on heapes, how ſhall the Engine goe.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Another of them had got a fine device to make Veſſels rowe themſelves againſt Wind and Tide, alſo he would have a moſt curious Dinner ſerved by inviſible hands out of the water, on a Table, and be ſet into a Barge; and a Dragon ſhould flye all the while over the Barge, and ſpit out of his mouth Bottles of moſt rich Wine; this ſhould have beene ſhowed upon the Thames, but when it came to the ſerving up of the Dinner, it would not doe; whereupon he had no other excuſe, <hi>But a poxe on't, ſome body had cut his Cable:</hi> Now you muſt underſtand that none of theſe famous fellowes, but either had or ſought moſt earneſtly to have a <hi>Patent</hi> of Priviledge to engroſſe theſe <hi>Projects</hi> ſolely to themſelves, pretending no benefit at all to them, but onely ſo farre forth as to defray their neceſſary expences, but all the profit to acrew onely to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56762:19"/> his Majeſtie, and the good of the Common-wealth, which how falſe they are, the ſucceſſe of theſe ſeverall <hi>Projects</hi> in this Age will ſhew to every one. Theſe <hi>Projects</hi> had very ill ſucceſſe, becauſe as I have ſhewed you, they had every one of them ſome great faults, as inſufficiency, exceeding dearneſſe, exceeding baſeneſſe or uglineſſe.</p>
               <p>The new Waterworkes to raiſe Waters being leſſe ſufficient for the purpoſe then the old way, and more chargeable to be erected, and in regard of excellency more imperfect, became a worthleſſe <hi>Project.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The new Invention of melting Iron from the Oare with Seacoale, had one of the before recited faults; for though it may be melted that way, yet the good Mettali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call quality of the Iron is deſtroyed, or at leaſt the greateſt part of it; for there is a certaine Arſenicall, or Antimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all quality in all ſubterraneall ſubſtances combuſtible, both which are poyſons to Iron, and make it altogether inſufficient.</p>
               <p>The Engine to ſowe Wheat was leſſe excellent then the old ordinary way of ſowing.</p>
               <p>The Invention of making Windowing of pure Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice Glaſſe, the ſale Mechanicke was exceeding deare, and coſtly, and therfore although it be more excellent or more ſufficient then the ordinary kinde of Windowing by greene Glaſſe, yet the Projector can doe no good of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath the fault of exceeding deareneſſe.</p>
               <p>The great Imperiall Engine before ſpoken of was to bee tryed amongſt the whole Company of <hi>Projectors</hi> but when the fire was given, it being overtaken by miſtake of meaſure, and moderation (a matter which <hi>Projectors</hi> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome regard, and ſpends ſo much money in fundamentall tryals as they call them) it ſodainly recoyled and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56762:19"/> in the diſcharge tooke <hi>Pompeon Bread</hi> ſuch a blow on the boſome, that he was preſently carryed off, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver likely to repaire to the Court againe, untill a deare yeare repaire his reputation.</p>
               <p>The Fulling Milners famous woodden Horſe not like the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe uſed to Warre, ſtarted at the mighty cracke, caſt his burthen, and before he came to <hi>Iſlington,</hi> brake one of his hinder legs, by which he became utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unſerviceable, and not long after alſo gave up his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraleld life, bequeathing his vaſte body (like <hi>Tom Lank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords Gelding</hi>) to his Maſter for Winter fuell to comfort his melancholly ſoule.</p>
               <p>Theſe things and many others falling out very contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this brave couragious minde, caſt him into an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable conſumption of <hi>Conceit,</hi> although he was a while <hi>palliated</hi> by ſome letters from others his fellowes, of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſucceſſe upon another triall, but all would not ſerve turne; his Phyſitians found that he was much troubled with a <hi>Reference,</hi> but was a little lightned by a <hi>cordiall Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate,</hi> yet in the end no Phyſicke could be adminiſtred that could worke with him, but of an extraordinary ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſtopping at the <hi>Great Seale,</hi> he ſhortly after dyed.</p>
               <p>Since whoſe death I finde that in the time of his ſicknes, be made his laſt Will and Teſtament in writing, deſiring that there might be an Office erected of purpoſe for the enroling of the ſame, and of others his ſucceſſors, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhewed himſelfe a true <hi>Projector</hi> both in life and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="mock_will">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56762:20"/>
               <head>The Projectors laſt Will and Teſtament.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN the name of the great Egerian Nympha, propitious Patroneſſe of all</hi> Projectors, <hi>ſince ſhe firſt inſpired her</hi> Pomphilius <hi>the moſt Potent that ever was of that Profeſsion. J that was before buſied in making, and framing of Common-wealths, as my leaſt Imployment, am now become no more then an ordinary mortall man, making my laſt Will and Teſtament in manner and forme following:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imprimis,</hi> I will that my tenth part in the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Lottery be beſtowed in the building of an Hoſpitall, to which the maimed <hi>Projectors</hi> that have miſcarried ſhall be conveyed to be there
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56762:20"/> well provided for, recovered, and made ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> My will is, that if any Courtier after my deceaſe prove ſo miraculouſly honeſt as to performe to mine Executors what hee contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with me in my life time, it bee disburſed in the erecting of certaine <hi>Almes-houſes</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite only of ſuch as have conſumed their eſtates in attending for great Preferments, Offices, Clerkſhips, and Surveyors places, upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull proofe and ſucceſſe of <hi>Projects;</hi> and one of theſe Almeshouſes I thinke fit to bee built in <hi>Ramme Alley,</hi> where they may have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Temple Garden, and Gallery to free them from the leſt ſuſpition of danger, for of all Spices the very ſight of the Mace frights them almoſt into a quotidian Ague; another I would have to be in <hi>Milford Lane,</hi> where I have found good refuge my ſelfe at a pinch; the third to be in <hi>Fulwoods Rents</hi> in <hi>Holborne,</hi> for the benefit of <hi>Grayes Inne,</hi> and <hi>Purpoole Lane</hi> for their outlet, and the fourth to be in <hi>Mountague Cloſe</hi> for their Summer houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I give and bequeath all that piece of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56762:21"/> ground lying betweene the trees in the Inner Temple on the Eaſt ſide to be a Summer walke for Gentlemen of that Profeſsion for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I give and bequeath unto the ſaid <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> the long <hi>Wooden Gallery</hi> extending over the Middle Temple Lane going towards the Water ſide, to be their Winter retyring place for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I likewiſe bequeath my whole ſhare of the <hi>Moytie</hi> of the late <hi>Project,</hi> for pickling of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers Weſtward towards the repairing of the ſaid Gallery now much decayed, and for the gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the ſaid Windowes there, that the Siſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonian heads of our <hi>Projectors</hi> be not endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged by reaſon of the cold, and ſo their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes become ayrie and unprofitable.</p>
               <p>Provided alwayes, that if any of them ſhall be heard to talke of any leſſe ſome of money then thouſands in either of the ſaid places, they forthwith loſe the benefit of this preſent Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I further bequeath unto the ſaid <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56762:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> and their ſucceſſors the whole profit that ſhal ariſe and acrew in and by the late invention of the ſole making and erecting certaine profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Stoves for roaſting, baking, boyling of all meates, and drying of Mault without ſight of fire, or touch of ſmoake, whereby the food is not corrupted, and the liquor ſo much more ſubtile for and towards the ſtaying of their ſharpe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks before dinner time, upon this condition, that their morning meeting for this purpoſe ſhall be at the <hi>Welſh Ordinary in Chancery Lane,</hi> and their dyet no other then what ſhall be coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and dreſſed by the ſaid invention that their wits may be refined, and ſo exceed ordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I give and bequeath unto the Salt-Peter men aforeſaid my little Tenement by the Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Ponds to be their Worke-houſe for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I give and bequeath unto the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> aforeſaid all my Inſtruments and Tooles <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent,</hi> and <hi>Tranſient,</hi> both <hi>Plegnicke, Lenicke,</hi> and <hi>Caminicke,</hi> as <hi>Preſſes, Vices, Screwes, Bellowes, Tongues, Moulds, Dryers, Rammers,</hi> and all my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56762:22"/> whatſoever, with their and every of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtnances which are at my Workehouſe at <hi>Iſllington Highbury,</hi> or elſewhere within theſe his Majeſties Realmes and Dominions of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> I give and bequeath unto my brethren the Brokers of <hi>London</hi> my whole ſtanding War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drobe, in hope that they will Regiſter this deed, and for the Donators ſake for ever obſerve the Vigils of Saint <hi>Hugh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Funerall I will paſſe over as not worth ſpeaking of, onely I will beſtow an Epitaph on him, which is the laſt point of ſervice that I can doe him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>And may this Story many Ages after,</l>
                  <l>For loſſe of our <hi>Projector</hi> move much laughter.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="mock_epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>EPITAPH.</head>
            <l>REader if thou faine would'ſt know</l>
            <l>who lies here entomb'd below,</l>
            <l>Know 'tis one who in his time</l>
            <l>the Common-wealth ſtriv'd to refine:</l>
            <l>All Trades now uſ'd ſeem'd to him toyes</l>
            <l>as if th'ad been devis'd by boyes;</l>
            <l>He had ſuch wayes to mend the ſame</l>
            <l>That got him an admired name</l>
            <l>With many friends and riches ſtore</l>
            <l>yet for all this he died poore.</l>
            <l>All you therefore that this way paſſe</l>
            <l>and caſt your eye upon theſe lines</l>
            <l>Lament our brave <hi>Projectors</hi> loſſe,</l>
            <l>who hath not left his like behind;</l>
            <l>For here he lies got wealth and lands</l>
            <l>that now wants ſtrength to ſtirre his hands.</l>
            <l>And here beleeve it he hath found,</l>
            <l>after many a weary looke</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>A parcell of concealed ground,</l>
            <l>never came in <hi>Tippers</hi> Booke,</l>
            <l>Let him have this little quillet,</l>
            <l>for his Wormes, and he will fill it.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56762:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
